Welcome back to APUSH in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. Take a look at this man. He
looks pretty cool. But then, take a look
at the guy next to him. It's the same
dang person. Yeah, that's right. This is
basically the 1950s in American history.
The reason I say that is because during
the 50s, people across the country
started living very similar lives,
meaning American culture became
increasingly homogeneous. Now, it's
pretty easy to see why this is the case.
The television becomes massive and every
American is watching them. And to add to
that, TV shows promote a nuclear family,
meaning where the husband works and the
wife stays at home. Shows also showed
suburban life and traditional gender
roles. So now everyone is watching and
being influenced by the same things. But
it's not just that. The economic boom of
the 50s also means everyone is buying
the same stuff, such as cars,
appliances, and again, TVs. And now with
Americans living in the suburbs, again,
remember this is what an American
neighborhood looks like. It's all the
same. So when you look at the 50s in
American history from a cultural
standpoint, the big label you can truly
give it is calling it conformist,
meaning people are following the same
norms, expectations, and lifestyles.
Now, though what I said is all true, it
wasn't technically all the same. There
is some pushback against conformity in
this time period. Let's go through some
examples. The Beat movement happened,
where writers and poets rejected
consumerism and traditional values. Rock
and roll surged with artists like Chuck
Berry and Elvis Presley. I mean, listen
to this song by Elvis.
Sorry, that's all I can play so I don't
get copyrighted. The last two things
here are intellectual criticism of
aspects of American culture. And also,
there were early movements in the LGBTQ+
movement, with an example being the
Mattachine Society, which were one of
the earliest, most influential US gay
rights organizations. On the screen now
are AP-style questions for this topic.
Pause now.
I will
I will see you in the next one.